<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mystery of the two ivntos Presbyterian and independent. Or, The serpent in the bosome vnfolded.</title>
            <author>Walker, Clement, 1595-1651.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B10258</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80925259</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W332A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R235062</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80925259</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 80925259</idno>
            <idno type="VID">192162</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B10258)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 192162)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2901:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mystery of the two ivntos Presbyterian and independent. Or, The serpent in the bosome vnfolded.</title>
                  <author>Walker, Clement, 1595-1651.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the yeare, 1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Author and place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:192162:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192162:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192162:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192162:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MYSTERY OF THE TWO IVNTOS PRESBYTERIAN and INDEPENDENT.</p>
            <p>OR, THE SERPENT IN THE BOSOME, VNFOLDED.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PETRON. ARBITER.</hi>
               </bibl> Omnes nobiſcum aut Corvi qui Lacerant, aut Cadavera quae lacerantur.</q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:192162:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:192162:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the un-byaſſed Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou that are byaſſed with <hi>ſelf-reſpects</hi> I write not to, you have your aimes; and your ends before you are aware, like ſhot not feared, till felt) will come upon you. To the upright <hi>in heart,</hi> though <hi>miſ led in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> I ſpeak. Conſider how by a <hi>prevaricating num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Grandees,</hi> our <hi>firſt Principles</hi> are altered; our <hi>Religion into Schiſme,</hi> and <hi>Hypocriticall profanenes;</hi> Inſomuch that the Lords Supper is now almoſt every where diſcontinued, for want of (I know not what) imaginary <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topian holineſſe. The Creed Lords Prayer, and Ten Commandements, (the inſtruments of Faith, Hope, Charity, teaching <hi>Omnia credenda, ſperanda, &amp; facienda</hi>) left out of the Directory. Thus much for Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our known Laws</hi> (being the <hi>ſecond Principle</hi> held out to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by the Nationall Covenant, and many Declarations) are turned into <hi>Arbitrary, emergent, and upſtart Orders and Ordinances of</hi> Parliament: every day riſing, and every day withering like Muſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romes. So that we are now governed <hi>Jure vago &amp; incerto,</hi> by a lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Lesbian rule, to which we cannot ſquare our obedience and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but muſt ſtay till the Grandees that guide the Legiſlative power of Parliament make application of them to our actions. A great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The third Principle is our Liberties.</hi> What is become of them, this little Treatiſe will tell you, as alſo of our Properties. But ſtay! me thinks I heare men ſay that the clamour and danger mutining at the Parliament door theſe two laſt weeks, hath humbled our Grandees, and made them ſeek the <hi>Lord</hi> with <hi>Faſting and Prayer.</hi> I anſwer, let mee tell you what ſucceeded in the Houſe of Commons, when a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Declaration from the Army being tendred to be read, ſome of the Grandees anſwered, That if they ſhould read thoſe demands, they might chance to find them of that nature, as they can neither with juſtice deny them, nor with honour grant them, becauſe it was not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable for them to doe their duty upon admonition of their Army, being but their ſervants, and would ſavour of compulſion. To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent this, they reſolved to take into confideration freely and of their
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:192162:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> owne accord the <hi>Grievances</hi> which ſcandalized the people. They went therefore upon <hi>3.</hi> Heads: <hi>The Self-denying Ordinance.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which they Voted (as they ſaid by a Preparatory Vote onely) That all Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers holding any Offices, Grants, or Places by conceſſion of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, ſhall account for, and pay in the profits thereof to the Grand Committee of Accounts. This I conceive under favour of the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees, who poſſeſſe thoſe places, and contrived this Vote (to be a meer deluſory Order, For who can beleeve that ſuch ſelf-ſeeking men, as all men know them to be, will execute theſe offices for nothing, and pay in to the uſe of the State their profits. Beſides, it is apparent how ſubſervient to theſe Grandees, their own creatures, the Committee of Accounts are.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> They Voted, That no money hereafter ſhould be given to any Member in <hi>compenſation or recompence of his loſſes,</hi> untill the Publick Debts be paid. Here the Grandees were in earneſt, becauſe their owne turnes are already ſerved, and the loſſe and inconvenience of this Vote falls only upon the much contemned <hi>Middle</hi> or <hi>Moderate Members.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> They appointed a Committee to conſider how to take off the Grievance ariſing from ſuch Members as abuſing the Priviledge of Parliament refuſe to pay their debts.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Proh Superi, quantum mortalia pectora caecae</l>
               <l>Noctis habent; Ipſe ſceleris molimine Tereus</l>
               <l>Creditur eſſe pius; laudem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> a crimine ſumit.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Let not the Grandees be offended, that I diſcover thoſe ſickneſſes which they labour to cover; <hi>Antea morbos, neceſſe eſt, cognitos eſſe, quam remedia eorum.</hi> God onely can be the <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> and cure them. But I am afraid they deſire rather a ſlight ſuppurating, then a perfect cure; and that they pray rather to hide, then help their evils.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Da fallere, da juſtum, ſanctum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> videri</l>
               <l>Noctem peccatis, &amp; fraudibus objice nubem.</l>
            </q>
            <p>If this be their condition, <hi>quos perdere vult Jupiter, hos demen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat; quos tueri vult, ſuſcitat.</hi> I have done my duty, even in this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, <hi>quando dicere quod nolo miſerum, quod volo &amp; debeo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculoſum.</hi> I leave the ſucceſſe to God, reſting,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thine,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THEODORUS VERAX.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:192162:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Myſterie of the two Iuntos, <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Independent.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Kingdome being overgrowne with <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Corruption,</hi> and <hi>Superſtition</hi> (the fruits of a long and lazie peace) by a long diſcontinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Parliaments; At laſt by Providence his Majeſtie was neceſſitated to call a Parliament the onely Colledge of Phyſitians to purge the much diſtempered body of the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>In this Parliament a conteſt betweene the <hi>Kings Prerogative</hi> and <hi>the peoples lawes and liberties</hi> begat a warre. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The <hi>Divines</hi> on both ſides out of their pulpits ſounding Alarme thereto: and not only <hi>Sermons;</hi> but <hi>Declarations of Parliament,</hi> and <hi>the Nationall Covenant,</hi> (holding forth to the people the defence of Religion, Laws, Liberties, and properties) inflamed the people to the rage of battle, as the Elephant is inraged at the ſight of Red. This warre occaſioned extraordinary Taxes and leavies of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, ſuch as was never heard of by our Anceſtours, and were <hi>Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritamenta malorum,</hi> the nurſe of our Corruptions.</p>
            <p>This incentive working upon the humane frailty of the ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and leading members of the Houſes,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Grandees.</hi>
               </note> cauſed them firſt to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terweave their particular intereſts and ambitions with the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, and laſtly to preferre them before the publique.</p>
            <p>Wherefore the ſaid <hi>Leading men or Grandees</hi> (for that is now Parliament language.<note place="margin">4. <hi>Factions.</hi>
               </note>) Firſt divided themſelves into <hi>two factions or Junto's: Presbyterians,</hi> and <hi>Independents:</hi> ſeeming to look only upon the Church, but (Religion having the ſtrongeſt operation upon the ſpirit of man) involved the intereſts of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
            <p>The Common people of the two houſes following (with an implicite faith and blind obedience) the example of their leaders, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> divided themſelves alſo into the ſaid Dichotomy; which they did with more ſeriouſneſſe then their leaders, as not perceiving any thing of deſigne therein: But according to the diverſity of their judgements, or rather fancyes and confidings (for to reſigne a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:192162:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> mans judgement to the opinion of another man is but a ſilly truſt and confidence) ſtudied the to holding of their parties with ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe; whilſt the Grandees of each party in private cloſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for their owne advancement, ſerving one anothers turn.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The <hi>Grandees</hi> (in all publique debates) ſeeme as reall in their reciprocall oppoſitions, as thoſe ſilly ones who are in earneſt, whereby they cheriſh the zeal of their reſpective partyes, keepe them ſtill divided, (<hi>Divide &amp; impera</hi> is the devils rule) and ſo amuſe them, and take them off from looking after other intereſts, in which (were they conjoyned) they might ſhare with the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees themſelves: and for the better contentment of ſuch their Confidents as look too intentively after their own gain, the Grandees of each <hi>Junto</hi> conferre ſomething of advantage upon thoſe that are ſubſervient to them, as five pounds a week, or ſome petty imployment.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The ſeeds of theſe factions ſpread themſelves into the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth and Armies: as Rheume diſtils from the Head into all the body.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>8</hi> Monopoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Profits and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</note>Thus the leading men or Bell-wethers have <hi>ſeemingly divided themſelves,</hi> and having <hi>really divided the Houſes:</hi> and captivated their reſpective parties judgement, teaching them by an Implicite faith <hi>Jurare in verba Magiſtri,</hi> to pinne their opinions upon their ſleeves; They begin to advance their Projects of Monopolizing the profits, preferments and Power of the Kingdome in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. To which purpoſe, though the leaders of each party ſeem to maintain a hot oppoſition, yet when any profit or preferment is to be reached at; It is obſerved that a powerfull Independent eſpecially moves for a Presbyterian: or a leading Presbiterian for an Independent: and ſeldome doth one oppoſe or ſpeak againſt another (in ſuch caſes) unleſſe ſomething of particular ſpleen or Competition come between, which cauſeth them to break the common Rule. By this meanes the Grandees of each faction ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome miſſe their mark, ſince an Independent moving for a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian, his reputation carries the buſineſſe cleare with the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent party: and the Presbyterians will not oppoſe a leading man of their own ſide. By this artifice the Grandees of each ſide ſhare the Common wealth between them: And are now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come proud, domineering Rehoboams (even over the reſt of their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:192162:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> follow members<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> contrary to the liberty of Parl. which conſiſts in an equality) that were formerly fawning ambitious <hi>Abſoloms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There hath been lately given away to members openly (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides innumerable and ineſtimable private cheates mutually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nived at) at leaſt 300000 l. in money; beſides rich offices, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments in money Committees, Sequeſtrations, and other ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages. And thoſe members who have ſo well ſerved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under colour of ſerving the publique, are (for the moſt part) old Canvaſers of Factions who have ſate idly and ſafely in the houſe watching their advantages to confound buſineſſes, and ſhuffle the cardes to make their owne game, when others that have ventured their perſons abroad, labour'd in the publick work like <hi>Iſaelites</hi> under theſe <hi>Egyptian</hi> task-maſters, and loſt their eſtates, are left to ſterve, untill they can find reliefe in that empty bag, called by fooles <hi>fides publica,</hi> by wiſe men <hi>fides punica.</hi> And are now looked upon in the Houſe ſuperciliouſly, like unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come gueſts (for it is known how malignantly and how jugling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly writs for new elections were granted and executed) and called <hi>younger brothers,</hi> and like younger brothers they are uſed: their elder brothers having ſlipped into the world before them, and anticipated the inheritance; They have broken firſt into the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon field, and ſhut the dore to prevent after commers even from gleaning after their full harveſt. For the better effecting whereof they have now morgaged (in effect) all the meanes they have to raiſe money, unto the City. And being themſelves fat and full with the publike Treaſure (to expreſſe rather their ſcorne then care.) Ther are making an Ordinance that no more money ſhall be given to their members: And yet to ſhew how carefull they are of all ſuch as have <hi>cheated</hi> the Common-wealth <hi>under them</hi> (I will not ſay <hi>for them</hi>) They have taken advantage of the petition of the Army: wherein they deſired Indempnity for all acts done in relation to the warre. And have paſſed an Ordinance of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnity for all ſuch, as have acted <hi>by authority,</hi> and <hi>for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</hi> of the Parliament, wherein (under great penalties, &amp; with an app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ale at laſt from the Judges of the Law, to a Comittee of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament) ſuch as have gone beyond the authority given by Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and ſequeſtred men unjuſtly and ſo withheld their goods under pretence thereof, and ſuch as have leavied taxes three or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:192162:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> four times over, are quit from private actions: and the benefite of Law and Juſtice taken from the Oppreſſed, to ſecure <hi>countrey Committees, Sequeſtrators,</hi> and others, (not <hi>Prerogative,</hi> but <hi>Legiſlative) Theeves;</hi> contrary to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> which ſaies,, <hi>nulli negabimus, nulli differemus juſtitiam, aut rectum;</hi> We will deny, or deferre juſtice and right to no man. Oh prodigious acts! and of greater tyranny then any King ever durſt adventure upon. What is become of our <hi>Nationall Cov.</hi> and the Parliament many <hi>Declarations</hi> for defence of Lawes and Liberty? Or have we fought our libertie into ſlavery? By theſe deviſes the <hi>honeſt middle men</hi> of the Houſe (whoſe conſciences will not let them joyn in any faction to rend the Common-wealth in ſunder) are out of all poſſibility of repaire, and made contemptible as well by their own want, as the pride of the Grandees: and in the end, their poverty will inforce them to leave the ſole poſſeſſion of the houſe to theſe <hi>thriving Junto men,</hi> who do beleaguer them therin, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them (for farther addition to their loſſes) pay all taxes from which the thriving men go free: ſo that the poorer part of the houſe payes tribute to the richer. Nay it is further whiſpered, that at laſt the <hi>Junto men</hi> will quit the Parliament Priviledge of not being ſued, purpoſely to leave theſe younger Brothers to the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of their Creditors, and diſable them to ſit in their Houſe.</p>
            <p>An other ambitious ayme of thoſe <hi>Junto men</hi> is their deviſe of referring all buſineſſes of moment <hi>to Committees.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>10.</hi> Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees of the Houſes.</note> For the active ſpeaking men by mutuall agreement, naming one another of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Committee (or at leaſt their confident Miniſters) doe thereby <hi>fore-ſtall and intercept</hi> the buſineſſes of the houſe, and under co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of examining and preparing matters, they report them to the houſe with what gloſſes, additions, detractions, and advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges they pleaſe; whereby the Houſe (judging according to their report) oftentimes miſ-judgeth, and if it be a buſineſs they are willing to ſmoother, the Committees have infinite artificiall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes to put it off, and keep it from a hearing, or at leaſt from reporting. By this meanes the remaining part of the Houſe are but cyphers to value, and Suffragans to ratifie what is fore-judged by the ſaid Committees. This uſurpation of theirs is much helped by keeping the doors of their Committee roomes ſhut, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patching all affaires privately and in the darke. Whereas Juſtice
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:192162:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> delights in the light, and ought to be as publique as the common aire, it being againſt its nature to be chambred up and kept from the obſervation of eye, and eare witneſſes.</p>
            <p>Parts of this project wee may well call the <hi>Multiplicity of money Committees,</hi> as Goldſmiths hall, Haberdaſhers hall,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>11.</hi> Money Committees.</note> the Committee of the Kings revenues, Committee of the Army, &amp;c. Where every mans profit and power is according to his cunning and conſcience. Hereby they draw a generall dependency after them, for he that commands the money, commands the men: Theſe Committee-men are ſo powerfull that they over-awe and over-power their fellow members, contrary to the nature of a free Parliament: wherein the equallity of the members muſt main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the freedome and integrity thereof, and ſuppreſſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
            <p>The like may be ſaid of ſuch <hi>members as</hi> (in ſcorne of the <hi>ſelf-denying Ordinances) hold offices by gift or connivence</hi> of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: either <hi>openly</hi> in their own name,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>12.</hi> Members holding offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp;c.</note> or <hi>Secretly</hi> in the name of ſome friend. Their offices inabling them to do courteſies and diſcourtiſes. And although there hath bin a Committee appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to certifie all penſions, Sequeſtrations, offices, imployments of advantage and profits conferred by the Parliament upon any their members, in which Committee <hi>M. Sands</hi> holdeth the chair; yet is this meerly a formallitie to blind the eyes of the world, and foole the expectation of ſome loſing members, who were then reſolute to know who had already received ſatisfaction for their loſſes, and how farre they had outrunne their fellow-members therein. Yet this Committee is now let fall, no reports deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of <hi>M. Sand:</hi> and when any is to be made; they are not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provided of a meanes to make it fruitleſſe, by putting every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular to debate: well knowing that no man will be willing to argue againſt the particular perſons and merits of his fellow-members, and thereby heape envie upon his own head; beſides the delay of a particular debate.</p>
            <p>How frequently the <hi>countrey Committees</hi> act contrary to the Laws of the Land:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>13.</hi> Countrey Committees.</note> how they trample <hi>Magna Charta</hi> under their feet, how boldly and avowedly they tranſgreſſe all orders and Ordinances of Parliament, and break our ſolemne League and Covenant, how they ordinarily turne well affected men out of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:192162:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> their free-holds and goods, impriſon and beat their Perſons with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any known charge, accuſer, or witneſſe againſt them. How fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently they leavie one taxe three or four times over &amp; continue their leavyes after the Ordinances expire. How cruelly they raiſe the twentieth and fifth part upon the well affected; exerciſing, an Illegall arbitrary tyrannicall power over their fellow ſubjects farre higher then ever <hi>Strafford</hi> or <hi>Canterbury</hi> durſt adviſe the King to. How ignorantly and unjuſtly they exerciſe a power <hi>to hear and determine</hi> (or rather to determine without hearing, or heare without underſtanding) <hi>private controverſies of Meum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; Tuum, for debts, treſpaſſes,</hi> nay <hi>title and poſſeſſion of lands</hi> without either formality or knowledge of the Law, not having wit, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners nor breeding enough (as being choſen for the greateſt part, out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the baſeſt of the people for baſe ends) to ſatisfy men with an outſide, or Complement of juſtice: Inſomuch that nothing is now more Common, then an accuſation without an Accuſer, a ſentence without a Judge, and a condemnation without a hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. If any man, I ſay, be ſo deaf as not to heare the loud univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall outcrying of the people; ſo great a ſtranger in our Iſrael as not to know this truth, let him peruſe <hi>M. Edward Kings</hi> diſcovery of the arbitrarie actions of the Com. of <hi>Lincolne</hi> printed 1647. where he may ſee theſe things brieſty Epitomiſed: but to hiſtoriſe them at large would require a volume as big as the book of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs.</hi> Theſe Committees are excellent ſpunges to ſuck money from the people, and to ſerve not onely their owne, but alſo the Covetous, Malicious, Ambitious ends of thoſe that raked them out of the dunghill for that imployment, and doe defend them in their oppreſſions. Who is ſo blind as not to ſee that theſe men have theïr protectors? Their <hi>Daemones</hi> to whom they offer up part of their rapins; to whom they ſacrifice.</p>
            <q>Occulta ſpolia, &amp; plures de pace Triumphos.</q>
            <p>If there be any intention to reſtore our lawes and liberties, and free us from arbitrary Government: it is fit theſe Committees and all aſſociations be laid downe, having no enemy to aſſociate againſt, and that the old forme of Government by Sheriffes, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of the Peace &amp;c. be re-eſtabliſhed; and the <hi>Militia</hi> in each County ſetled as before, in Lieutenants, and Deputy-Lieutenants, or in Commiſſioners.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:192162:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Nor is it a ſmall artifice to raiſe mony by ſo <hi>many ſeverall and confuſed Taxes.</hi> Whereas one or two wayes orderly uſed and well husbanded, would have done the work. 1. Royall Subſidie of 400000 l. 2. Pole-mony. 3 the free Loans and contributions upon the publick Faith amounted to a vaſt incredible ſumme, in mony, Plate, horſe, Armes, &amp;c. 4. The Iriſh adventure for ſale of Lands the firſt and ſecond time. 5. The Weekly Meale. 6. the City Loane after the rate of 50 Subſidies. 7. The Aſſeſſement for bringing in the Scots. 8. the 5. and 20 part, 9. The Weekly aſſeſsement for my L. Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls Army. 10. The weekly (or Monthly Aſseſsement for Sir <hi>Tho. Fairfax</hi> Army. 11. The weekly Aſſeſsement for the Scottiſh Army. 12. The weekly Aſseſsement for the britiſh Army in <hi>Ireland.</hi> 13 The Weekly Aſseſsement for my L. of <hi>Manchesters</hi> Army. 14. Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quarter (at leaſt) connived at by the State, becauſe the Souldiers ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for a time ſubſiſtence that way, are the leſse craving for their pay: whereby their arrears growing ſtale, will at laſt either be fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by a tedious Committee of Accounts, or forgotten. In the mean time, the grand Committee of accounts diſcount it out of the Commanders arrears, whereby the State ſaves it. 15. The Kings Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue. 16. Sequeſtrations and plunder by Committee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, which if well anſwered to the State would have carried on the work: which thus I demonſtrate, One half of all the goods and chattells, and at leaſt one half of all the Lands, Rents, and Revenues of the Kingdom have been ſequeſtred. And who can imagine that one half of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits and goods of the Land will not maintain any Forces that can be kept and fed in <hi>England,</hi> for the defence thereof? 17. Exciſe upon all things. This alone if well mannaged would maintain the Warre. The Low-countries make it almoſt their onely ſupport. 18. Fortification money, &amp;c. By theſe ſeverall wayes and Taxes about 40 <hi>millions</hi> in money and money worth have been milked from the People: and the Parliament as (the Pope did once) may call England, <hi>Puteum inexhauſtum;</hi> yet is now almoſt drawn day. A vaſt Treaſury, and ſo exceſſive, as nothing but a long peace could import: and nothing but much fraud and many follies could diſſipate. And we ought not to wonder if it be accounted <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nter ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cana
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:192162:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> noviſſimi imperii</hi> to be alwayes making, yet never finiſhing an account thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">15. <hi>Accounts.</hi>
               </note>And as they have artificially confounded the accompts by laying on multiplicity of Taxes; ſo (ſo for the ſame reaſon) they let the money run in ſo many muddy, obſcure channells, through ſo many Committees and Officers fingers, both for collecting, receiving, iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and paying it forth, that it is impoſſible to make or ballance any publick account thereof: and at the leaſt one half thereof is known to be devoured by Committees and officers and thoſe that for lucre protect them. By theſe means as they make many men partners with them in the publick ſpoils, ſo they much ſtrengthen and increaſe their party, whereby <hi>multitude peccantium tollit paenam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Accounts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</note>If theſe things were not purpoſely done, 1. our Taxes would be fewer in number, and more in effect. 2. They would be put to run in one chanell, under the fingering of fewer Harpies, and perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous and true Entries made of all receipts and diſburſements which would be publick to common view and examination. The Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer way of Accompts is the exacteſt, ancienteſt, and beſt known way of account of <hi>England,</hi> and moſt free from deceit, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt confeſſed <hi>de facto,</hi> when (to make the Kings Revenue more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to their deſires) they took it out of the exchequer way (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the fundamentall Lawes of the Land; for both the higher &amp; lower Exchequer are as ancient and fundamentall as any Court in <hi>England</hi>) and put it under, a Committee which (as all other Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees do) wil render an account of their ſtewardſhip at the latter day. In the mean time divers of that Committee buy in old ſleeping Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which thee pay themſelves from the firſt of their arrears: yet other men that have diſburſed money out of their purſes for the Kings Service, can receive no pay for any money laid forth before <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Terme, 1643. becauſe (forfooth) then the Committee firſt took charge of the Revenue. In the mean time the Kings Tenants and debtours are deprived of the benefit of the Lawes and Liberties of the Subject which before they enjoyed: all Debts and Monies being now raiſed by the terrour of the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuivants and Meſſengers, whoſe Commiſſions are onely to diſtrain
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:192162:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> and levy, &amp;c. whereas formerly the Exchequer ſent out legall Proceſs, and the Tenant or Debtor had liberty to plead to it in his owne defence, if he thought himſelfe wronged; but now New Lords, new Lawes,, and to countenance their doings, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee have gotten an addition of ſome Lords to them. 3. If there were faire play above board, ſo many Members of both Houſes would not be ambitious of the trouble and clamour that attends Task-Maſters, Publicans, and ſuch ſinners as fit at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of Cuſtome, being no part of the buſineſſe for which the write ſummons, or the people chooſe or truſt them and whereby they are diverted from the buſineſſe of the Houſe: but would leave that imployment to other men, who not having the chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter and priviledge of Parliament upon them, will be leſſe able to protect themſelves and their agents from giving pub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ike accounts of their receips and disburſements, and from putting affronts &amp; delayes upon the Committee of Accompts as (it is well known) ſome of them have done. Laſtly it is ſcandalous that the ſame men ſhould be continued ſo long in their money imployments becauſe <hi>Diuturnitas &amp; ſolitudo corrumpunt Imperia;</hi> and by long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and experience they grow ſo hardned, ſo cunning in their way, and ſo backward with dependencies, that it is almoſt impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to trace them. And although (when we look upon the many perſons imployed) we cannot ſay there is <hi>ſolitudo perſonarum;</hi> yet when we conſider that by a long partnerſhip in their imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they are allyed together in one common intereſt; they are to be eſteemed but as one man, for a Corporation of men is but many men joyned together as one man, and with one mind pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing one and the ſame end or intereſt.</p>
            <p>And though we have a generall Committee of Accompts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>16.</hi> Committee of Accounts.</note> yet they were nominated by thoſe Members that ought to give Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts: and it muſt needs be ſuſpitious for an Accomptant to chooſe thoſe perſons before whom he ſhall accompt. And we ſee (after ſo long a time of their ſitting) no fruit thereof. Whereas the people did hope, that after ſo much money ſpent, and ſuch great debts and arreares left to pay, (whereby they are threatned with continuance of their Taxes) That a full and exact generall accompt of all Receipts and Disburſements would have been pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:192162:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> in Print, for their ſatisfaction, as is uſually done in the Low Countries, and as was once done by this Parliament, <hi>Anno</hi> 1642. by a Declaration of the accounts of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>17.</hi> Wants of the Parl. and how occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note>By theſe exorbitant courſes, though they have drayned 40. Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions from the people, yet (as <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> was ſaid to be <hi>Inter quotidianus rapinas ſemper inops</hi>) they are falne to ſuch ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous want and beggerie, that they have lately pawned almoſt all the ſecurity they have for 200000.l. to disband the Armie, and enter upon the Iriſh imployment. They have ſlit Goldſmiths Hall in ſunder, and given one ſide thereof to the Citie, and kept the other halfe thereof to themſelves, and that already charged with 200000.l. at leaſt. So that if any ſudden occaſion happen, they have put their purſe into the hands of the uncircumciſed Jews of the City, and cannot raiſe one peny but by new taxes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the people. It was worth obſerving to ſee how officiouſly ſome of the old Stagers took leave of the Publique purſe, before it came into Huckſters hands. Alderman <hi>Pennington</hi> had a debt of 3000. l. he owed to Sir <hi>Iohn Pennington</hi> forgiven him, (he never asked forgiveneſſe of his ſins ſo heartily) and 3000.l. more given him out of Goldſmiths Hall in courſe. The reaſon of this bounty was forked or two-fold:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe he had got enough before.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To comfort his heart, for being left out of the City Militia. But the moſt obſervable thing was, to ſee this old Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment like a young Prodigall, take up money upon difficult termes, and intangle all they had for a ſecurity.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They gave way to the City to hedge in an old debt, being a loane of money after the rate of Subſidyes: and other old debts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas 200000. l. only was the ſumme to be borrowed; the City injoyned them to take up 230000. l. whereof the the odde 30000. l. to be beſtowed for reliefe of decayed occupiers of the City: So, that (upon the matter) the Parliament payes 30000. l. Broakage.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the City may not truſt the greateſt unthrifts of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, with laying out their owne money; they put upon them two Treaſurers of the City to retaine and disburſe it for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:192162:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> for which it was borrowed. So ye ſee they have now neither credit, money, nor a purſe to put it in.</p>
            <p>So that the <hi>modeſt Members</hi> who have beene more forward to helpe their Country then themſelves,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>18.</hi> Modeſt and middle members.</note> are left in the lurch for their loſſes, and expoſed to the laughter of their elder brothers, the old <hi>Junto</hi> men, and factious leaders of the houſe; all being now morgaged to the <hi>Lombards</hi> of the City. The <hi>thriving Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> hope their younger brothers will continue as modeſt, as they have beene, and digeſt all with patience. But others (and thoſe neither fools nor knaves) hope all the <hi>modeſt and middle men</hi> of the houſes (ſuch as are ingaged in no faction) will be provoked here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to draw into a third party or <hi>Junto</hi> to moderate the exceſſes of the other two, when any thing prejudicial to the Common-wealth is agitated: and to call the old <hi>Junto</hi> men thoſe land Pyrates to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, making them caſt up what they have ſwallowed, and bring it to a common <hi>dividend.</hi> Nor let them be diſcouraged with the ſuppoſed difficulty hereof, ſince 20. or 30. men holding together, &amp; obſerving the croſſe debates, and different ſway of each party, may eaſily make themſelves moderators of their differences, &amp; turn the ſcales for the beſt advantage of the common, which way they pleaſe to caſt in their votes, ſince it is very rare to have any que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion carried by more then eight or tenne voyces.</p>
            <p>Moſt of theſe <hi>Grandees</hi> have for <hi>their retreat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>19.</hi> Grandees proviſion to ſave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</note> houſes in the Low Countryes richly furniſhed with ſequeſtred Plate, Linnen and Stuffe: and great ſtore of money in bank for their ſhelter, againſt ſuch ſtormes as their Rapine, Tyrannie and Ignorance may happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly raiſe here amongſt us. In thoſe their retirements, theſe Authors of our miſeries will injoy their ſinnes, and our ſpoiles in ſecurity, attending an opportunity to purchaſe their peace at laſt, and betray our Safeties and Liberties to the inraged Prince and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. This is called robbing the Aegyptians. And truly theſe am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious ſtate-Mountebanks have brought us into a darkneſſe, worſe then Aegyptian. The text faith, the Aegyptians roſe not from their places in three dayes: They yet knew where they were: which is more then we doe, every man being out of his place and ranck. The Servant in place of his Maſter, the Begger in place of the King, the Foole in place of the Councellour, the Theife
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:192162:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> in place of the Judge, the Cheater in place of the Treaſurer, the Clowne in place of the Gentleman; none but God alone can play <hi>Daedalus</hi> part, and give us a Clue to lead us out of this labyrinth, into which theſe unpolitique <hi>Hocas Pocaſſes</hi> have brought us: Theſe unskilfull workmen that have built up Babel, and pulled downe Sion. Others are ſaid to prepare Forraigne Plantations for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat; To people which, children are raviſhed from their parents armes, and Shipped away; an abomination not knowne in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land before, and therefore no competent Law made againſt it; no more then in ancient Rome againſt Parricides.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>20.</hi> Grandees their ſeveral intreſts and deſignes and ſtrengths.</note>By what hath been already ſaid, you ſee what the <hi>ſeverall,</hi> and what the <hi>conjoyned intereſts</hi> of theſe <hi>two Juntos</hi> or <hi>Factions Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian</hi> and <hi>Independent</hi> are. Let us now conſider where <hi>their ſeverall ſtrength</hi> lyes. The <hi>Independent</hi> groundeth his ſtrength upon the <hi>Army,</hi> which if he can keepe up, he hopes to give the Law to all; and to produce that great Chymaera, <hi>Liberty of Conſcience:</hi> not conſidering that the confuſion and licentiouſneſſe of ſuch a liberty will deſtroy it ſelfe, <hi>Libertas Libertate perit.</hi> The <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians</hi> have three <hi>pillars</hi> to ſupport them. 1. <hi>The City</hi> is their chiefe foundation, with which they keepe a ſtrict correſpondencie, and dayly communication of Councells. Upon this conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they have lately put the Parliament Purſe into the Cities Poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket as aforeſaid; ſetled and inlarged the City Militia. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as all the Countrys of England (being more obnoxious to injuries then the Citie) ſuffer much for want of ſetling their Militia; the Parliament not truſting them with armes, ſo much as for their owne defence: An evident ſigne, there is a farther deſigne then disbanding this Army. And becauſe the City Militia, can only keepe in awe the adjacent South and Eaſt Counties of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; therefore to ſuppreſſe the remoter parts, and inforce them to obedience, they keepe up ſome <hi>in-land Garriſons,</hi> and have <hi>Generall Poyntz ſupernumerarie forces</hi> for the North. And in <hi>the Weſt</hi> (under colour of ſending men for Ireland) they keepe upon free quarter and pay of the country <hi>many ſupernumerarie Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments</hi> and Troops moſt Cavaliers; at leaſt five times as many as they really intend to tranſport. Theſe are alwayes going, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver gone: Like Saint <hi>George,</hi> alwayes in his ſaddle, never on his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:192162:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> way. Something ever is and ſhall be wanting untill Sir <hi>Thomas Fayrfax's</hi> Army be disbanded; and then (it is thought) the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe will fall off; and theſe ſupernumeraries ſhall appeare a new modelled Army under Presbyterian Commanders, you may bee ſure: and ſuch whoſe conſciences ſhall not befoole their wits where any matter of gaine appeareth. If this be not their ayme, Why did they not disband theſe lewd Supernumeraries before laſt winter, ſince they might have raiſed as many men the ſpring following for halfe the charge their very free quarters coſt? And moſt of theſe ſweare they will not goe for Ireland, vowing they will cut the throats of the Round-heads.</p>
            <p>The Countrey is amazed, fearing theſe Cavaliers are kept on free-quarter by a Cavaleeriſh party for ſome Cavaleeriſh Deſigne. Secondly, why did they not rather divide Sir <hi>Thomas Fayrfax</hi> Army into two parts, one to goe for <hi>Ireland,</hi> the other to ſtay in <hi>England;</hi> being already modelled, excellently diſciplined, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the viſible marks of Gods favour upon their actions? But to take a few for <hi>Ireland,</hi> a few for <hi>England,</hi> and leave a Coare in the middle to be plucked forth and disbanded, was the way to diſcontent them, and put them into mutiny: and thereby neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Parliament to disband them all, and give an opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to them that ſeek it, to new modell another army out of the aforeſaid Supernumeraries, more plyable to the deſires of the Presbyterian <hi>Iuncto:</hi> Adde hereunto the cauſeleſſe exaſperating Speeches and aſperſions caſt upon moſt of the army purpoſely, as moderate men think, to diſcontent them. Thirdly, If they have no intent to keep up an Army upon the people, why have they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued the military charge for another yeare; and inlarge it from 52000 l. to 60000 l. a moneth?</p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>City, Inland Garriſons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">21. <hi>Presbytersi</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Supernumerarie forces new modelled</hi> are like to prove the three ſtringed whips wherewith the Presbyterian Phaetons will drive their triumphant Chariot if they prevaile; To which may be added <hi>the Presbytors</hi> themſelves, who by over-awing mens Conſciences with their Doctrine, will ſubdue and worke mens mindes like wax to receive any impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of bondage that tyranny and oppreſſion can ſet upon them, as they do in Scotland: The Clergy in all times and places have ever
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:192162:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> held with the mightyt as the Jacco hunts ſtill with the Lion to partake of his prey.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>23.</hi> Quaeries up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</note>The premiſes conſidered, I ſhall propound theſe enſuing <hi>Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> to thoſe that are of better Judgement then my ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Quere,</hi> Why the Title and puniſhment of Malignants is tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated from the Cavaliers, who fought for Regall Tyranny againſt the Parl. and laid upon thoſe that fought againſt Regall Tyranny for the Parliament? Is it not becauſe thoſe Cavaliers that have fought for one Tyrannie, will not be ſcrupulous to fight for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? and ſuch well affected as have oppoſed Tyranny in one kinde, will not admit of it in another? Why is it now accounted a note of malignity and diſaffection to endeavour the putting down of Arbitrary Government, and re-eſtabliſhing our lawes, liberties and properties; whereto the Parliament by their many Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and their Nationall Covenant are bound? Lay this to heart and conſider whether they have not changed theſe their firſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and conſequently whether they are not deſirous to change their old friends who reſolutely adhere to the ſaid principles.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the King grant the Propoſitions; or if he deny them, and the predominant <hi>Juncto</hi> (for both <hi>Juncto's</hi> joyned in one (for this is probable) to drive on one common intereſt) eſtabliſh the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary and civill power without him, according to their deſires, and in order to their aymes. <hi>Quaere</hi> whether the ſaid leading men ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in their poſtures with their confident Guards about them, may not draw after them ſo many of their party, as upon an implicite faith will follow them, and lick up the crums of the publicke ſpoyles under their Tables: expelling or diſabling (as aforeſaid) the diſ-ingaged members, and by this policy make themſelves per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall Dictators, incorporating and ingroſſing to themſelves both the Conſultive, Directive and Miniſteriall power of the Kingdome in all cauſes Civil and Military, ſetting up an <hi>Oligarchy</hi> or popular Tyranny in ſtead of a Regall: As the thirty Tyrants of <hi>Athens</hi> did. In order whereto they already declare, 1. That an Ordinance of Parliament without the Kings Royall aſſent is equall to an Act of Parliament. 2. That an Ordinance is above a Law by vertue of their Legiſlative power: upon which preſuming in their Ordinance of Indempnity they have granted an Appeale from the Judges of the Law to a Committee of Parliament. See the Ordinance <hi>May</hi> 21. 1647. 3. That they are the Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocable
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:192162:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> Truſtees of the peoples lawes, liberties and properties, without account: with other <hi>principles preparative to Tyranny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Quaere,</hi> Why Arbitrary and Barbarous Government by Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mittees and other Illegall proceedings (which in time of war were uſed upon Reall or pretended neceſſitie, &amp; were then only excuſable, becauſe <hi>neceſſitas tollit Legem</hi>) are ſtill continued upon us now in time of peace, no enemies troubling our quiet, and without any further pretence of neceſſitie, Contrary to their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Covenant, and all their Declarations? Is it not, to inure the People to ſervitude, and ever uſe their patience?</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Quaere,</hi> Whether the Prodigious oppreſſions of Committees, Sequeſtrators, &amp;c. and of free Quarter be not purpoſely counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced to neceſſitate the people to riſe in tumults, that thence occaſion may be taken to keepe in-land Garriſons and Armies?</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Quaere,</hi> Whether our lawes, liberties, and properties are not now as lyable to an Invaſion from the <hi>Legis-lative power,</hi> as formerly, from the <hi>Prerogative?</hi> Conſidering that thoſe who like ambitious <hi>Abſolom</hi> courted and wooed the people in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of troubles, now like haughtie <hi>Rehoboams,</hi> care not though the people complaine: Their little finger is heavier then the loynes of the King, the controverſie betweene the two <hi>Juncto's</hi> being no more, then whoſe ſlaves wee ſhall be.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>middle and diſ-ingaged men</hi> in the Houſe do not ſpeedily unite themſelves into a party or <hi>Juncto,</hi> as the Factious have done,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>23.</hi> Middle and Moderate members a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</note> and communicate their counſels; they will be <hi>arena ſine calce,</hi> looſe ſand diſſipated by every breath: and neither ſerviceable for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves nor their Countrey. Whereas if they unite, twentie or thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty may become Moderators and Umpeers between both parties; (as hath beene already ſaid) Let the moderate men but conſider how ſad and diſhonourable a thing it is to ſee nothing almoſt of great and publique concernment come into the Houſe, but what hath bin <hi>before hand contrived, debated, and digeſted</hi> in one or both of the two <hi>Juncto's</hi> at their <hi>private meetings:</hi> and put into ſo reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and prejudicate a way and method of diſpatch, that every man is appointed his part or Cue before-hand: One man to move it, and ſet it on foot, another to ſecond him: One man to ſpeake to one part of the argument, another to another part: another to keepe himſelfe to the laſt for a reſerve, and ſpeake to the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, which he is provided to qualifie with a diſtinction, or vary
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:192162:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> it, if he find it difficult to paſſe. Thus all publique buſineſſes are meaſured by private reſpects; wherby it appears, that as <hi>frequent Parl.</hi> are <hi>good phyſick:</hi> ſo continuall Parl. are <hi>bad food;</hi> &amp; the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may complain, that, <hi>qui medice vivit, miſere vivit.</hi> Parliaments are <hi>Bona peritura;</hi> they cannot keepe long without Corruption. Their perpetuitie emboldens the members, by taking from them all feare of being called to account: Eſpecially if they get their ſonnes into the Houſe as well as themſelves (as many have done this Parliament: and more endeavour to do) whereby they have an eſtate in their places for two or three lives: Moreover by long ſitting they become ſo familiar with one anothers perſons and deſignes, as to ſerve one anothers turnes, to joyn intereſt, and to draw into Factions, <hi>Hodie mihi, cras tibi.</hi> If you and your partie will helpe me to day, I and my friend will helpe you to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>24.</hi> Concluſion with ſome complaints.</note>
               <hi>Miſerima Reſp. ubi majeſtas Imperii, &amp; ſalus populi diſcordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus conflictantur ſtudiis.</hi> What ſhall we ſay?</p>
            <q>En quo diſcordia tetra—perduxit miſeros?</q>
            <p>Shall we complaine to God? God hath a controverſie with us. Of whom ſhall we complaine? of our ſelves? we muſt firſt reforme our ſelves: we that take upon us to reforme Church and Common-wealth. Shall we complaine of our ſinnes? aske the grace of repentance firſt; and ſo aske that we may obtaine. Shall we complaine of our puniſhments? let us firſt repent, and amend our ſins that cauſed them. Let us firſt pluck off the maske of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, God will ſee through ſuch a fantaſticall garment of Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaves. Let us no longer make Religion a ſtalking-horſe; God who is all Wiſedome, and all Truth, will not be deceived. If we talke like Chriſtians, and live like Turks, Chriſt will not owne us. To faſt for a day, and hang our heads like bulruſhes, will not reconcile us. We muſt faſt from publique ſpoiles, rapines and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and not drink the teares of the poore and needy. Shall we complaine with the Prophet, That our Princes are become Theeves? that was heretofore our complaint, now we muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert it, and cry, That our Theeves (meane and baſe people) are become Princes. We are ſick, very ſick, intemperately ſick; and God hath given us a Phyſitian in his wrath, a Leper as white as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:192162:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſnow, fitter to infect then cure us. What Phyſick doth hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe? Poyſon. What dyet? Stones inſtead of bread, Scorpions inſtead of fiſhes, hard fare for them that formerly fed ſo daintily. Before I conclude, let me give you the pedegree of our Miſeries, and of their Remedies. A long peace begat Plenty, Plenty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat Pride, and her ſiſter Riot; Pride begot Ambition, Ambition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got Faction, Faction begot Civill War: And (if our eviils be not incurable, if we be not falne <hi>in id temporis quo nec vitia noſtra, nec corum remedia ferre poſſumus</hi>) our War will beget Poverty, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty Humility, Humility Peace againe, <hi>Sic rerum revertentibus vicibus annulus vertitur Politicus.</hi> The declining ſpoake of the Wheele will riſe againe. But we are not yet ſufficiently Humb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; we have not repented with <hi>Nineveh.</hi> We weare Silkes and Velvets inſtead of ſack-cloath and aſhes (even the meaneſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtart hath his thefts writ upon his back by his Taylor in proud Characters of Gold-lace) we have not watered our Couch with our Teares, but with adulterous ſweat. Look to it therefore ye ſtate <hi>Incubi,</hi> that by an inceſtuous copulation have begot plenty upon Warre, and filled your houſes with the ſpoyle and plunder of your deare Countrey; an inundation of bloud, and of the tears of the oppreſſed will waſh away the foundation of your houſes: And peace will be farre from you in this world, but eſpecially that peace which the world cannot give: And becauſe <hi>Salaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>-like you delight in the fire of contention; an unquenchable fire will be your lot hereafter. And though you eſcape all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts here, yet upon the great day of account when you ſhall receive your ſentence of condemnation, thoſe your children for whoſe preferment you fell your ſoules, your God for gold, ſhall not ſhew ſo much thankfulneſſe or pitty towards you, as to ſay, alas our father! But your hearts are hardned with <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> I leave you therefore to <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> deſtiny, to be drowned in your owne Red Sea, as he was in his.</p>
            <p>Thus farre I adventured to vindicate our Religion, Lawes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>25.</hi> Reſolution and ſcope o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Author.</note> and Liberties with my pen; in diſcharge of my Conſcience, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of our Nationall Covenant which obligeth us to defend them againſt whoſoever to our power; neither knowing nor ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring whether in ſo wicked an age (wherein vice is honoured, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:192162:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> vertue contemned) I may be thought worthy of puniſhment for being more righteous then my ſuperiors. I know an honeſt man is wondred at like a monſter, and the innocency of his life and converſation ſuſpected as a Libell againſt the State, yet if I periſh I periſh; <hi>&amp; pereundum in licitis.</hi> Nor am I leſſe provided of a ſafe retreat then our Grandees. My grave is open for me, and one foot in it already. <hi>Contempſit omnes ille qui mortem prius.</hi> He that contemnes death, ſcornes both Hope and Feare; which are the only affections that make Knaves, Fooles and Cowards of all the world. The world is a goodly Theater, we the Actors, God is both Poet and chiefe ſpectator. We muſt not chooſe our owne parts, that is at Gods appointment. One man he appoints to play the King, another the Begger, one a Comick, another a Tragick part: Whatſoever part God hath appointed for me in this remainder of my life, I will have a care to perſonate it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuouſly and aptly: Not doubting but my <hi>Exit</hi> ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compained with an applauſe into my tyring Roome, my Tomb; nor will I refuſe the meaneſt part that may draw a plaudit from ſo excellent a ſpectator, but will prepare my ſelfe for the worſt of evills, in this worſt of times; and pray to God to reforme our Reformers. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:192162:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192162:14"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192162:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
